Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 68: Sexually Transmitted Infections.
Syphilis Gonorrhea Chlamydial Infection Herpes Simplex Virus Human Papillomavirus Vaginitis Human Immunodeficiency Virus References Sexually transmitted infections (STIs) include syphilis, gonorrhea, chlamydial and trichomonal infections, and infections caused by human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), herpes simplex virus (HSV), human papillomavirus (HPV), and hepatitis B and C viruses.
In describing their pathogenesis, horizontal transmission is transfer to a contemporary.
Instead, vertical transmission refers to passage of an infectious agent from the mother to her fetus through the placenta, during labor or delivery, or by breastfeeding.
Many STIs can harm the mother or fetus.
Thus, these are sought through both asymptomatic screening and symptomatic diagnostic testing and then treated.
For this, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) provides guidelines, which are described throughout this chapter.
For STI screening and diagnosis, serological testing is recommended in some cases and identifies antibodies formed by the patient against the pathogen.
In others, direct detection of an infectious agent by culture or by a nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) of body fluids or lesions is suitable.
NAATs include any molecular method used to detect the presence of DNA or RNA of a pathogen.
NAATs may be polymerase chain reaction (PCR) tests (most common), transcription-mediated amplification (TMA) tests, or others.
NAATs may be qualitative (detecting presence or absence only) or quantitative depending on the specific test.
The terms NAAT and PCR may be used interchangeably in some cases when appropriate.
If one STI is identified, patients are offered screening for all STIs, because these infections are commonly comorbid.
Treatment of most STIs is associated with improved pregnancy outcome and prevention of perinatal morbidity.
Logically, education, screening, treatment, and prevention are essential components of prenatal care.
Syphilis.
This infection remains a major threat for both mother and fetus.
Since 2001, the combined rate of primary and secondary syphilis has risen almost yearly, and among women in 2019, the rate was 4 cases per 100,000 persons .
For congenital syphilis, the rate in 2019 was 48 cases per 100,000 live births.
This is a nearly 300 percent rise since 2015.
Of risks, higher congenital syphilis rates are linked to inadequate prenatal care, substance use during pregnancy, African American race, and lack of screening and treatment .
The CDC also includes sex work, multiple or new sexual partners, incarceration, or homelessness .
Syphilis remains a significant global health problem .
# Pathogenesis.
Syphilis is caused by the spirochetal bacterium Treponema pallidum.
With horizontal transmission, minute abrasions on the vaginal mucosa provide entry, and cervical eversion, hyperemia, and friability raise this risk.
Spirochetes replicate and disseminate through lymphatic channels and then hematogenously if untreated.
During vertical transmission, spirochetes readily cross the placenta.
This is the most common route, but neonatal infection may result from contact with spirochetes from lesions at delivery or across the placental membranes.
Fetal infection develops in >50 percent of untreated early maternal syphilis cases and in up to 10 percent of late latent disease (Fiumara, 1975; Hollier, 2001).
# Clinical Manifestations.
Maternal Syphilis and Definitions This is staged according to clinical features and disease duration.
Primary syphilis is diagnosed by its characteristic chancre, which develops at the inoculation site.
Typically, a solitary, painless lesion has a raised, firm border and a red, smooth ulcerated base without significant pus .
Nonsuppurative lymphadenopathy may develop.
A chancre usually resolves spontaneously in 2 to 8 weeks, even if untreated.
Multiple lesions, if found, are predominantly in women with HIV co-infection.
Figure 68-1.
Primary syphilis.
Chancres show a raised, firm border and smooth base and may
be singular or multiple, as seen here.
Arrows point to two reciprocal or “kissing” lesions, which develop as infection on one side spreads to the other when tissues are apposed.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Allison J. Tracy, MD.) • Secondary syphilis stems from spirochete dissemination to multiple organ systems.
Manifestations develop 4 to 10 weeks after the chancre appears and include dermatological abnormalities in up to 90 percent.
A diffuse macular rash, plantar and palmar circular lesions, patchy alopecia, and mucous patches may be seen .
Condylomata lata are fleshcolored flat nodules found on the perineum and perianus.
Mucosal lesions teem with spirochetes and are highly infectious.
Women may have constitutional symptoms such as fever, headache, and myalgias.
Hepatitis, nephropathy, ocular changes, anterior uveitis, and periostitis are less common findings.
Manifestations of secondary syphilis resolve without treatment after 1 to 6 months, despite incomplete clearance of organisms by the immune system.
Figure 68-2.
Secondary syphilis.
A. Condyloma lata.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Ralynn Brann.
B. Target lesions on the palms.
C. Diffuse maculopapular rash.
With latent syphilis, clinical manifestations of primary or secondary syphilis either have resolved or were never recognized, but infection persists and is identified by serological testing.
Early latent syphilis is subclinical disease acquired within the preceding 12 months.
Timing of infection is determined by laboratory seroconversion results, clearly described symptoms consistent with primary or secondary syphilis within the prior 12 months, or exposure to a sexual partner in the previous 12 months with primary, secondary, or early latent syphilis.
If the duration of infection is either unclear or beyond 12 months, the term is latent syphilis, unknown duration or late.
Tertiary syphilis is a slowly progressive disease that affects any organ system but is rarely seen in reproductive-aged women.
Early-stage syphilis includes primary, secondary, and early latent syphilis.
These are associated with high spirochete loads, and partner transmission rates range from 30 to 60 percent (Garnett, 1997; Singh, 1999).
Late-stage syphilis includes latent syphilis, unknown duration or late and tertiary syphilis.
In these, transmission rates decline because of smaller inoculum sizes.
# Congenital Syphilis.
Without screening and treatment, approximately 70 percent of infected women will have an adverse pregnancy outcome .
Maternal infection can lead to congenital infection, preterm labor, low birthweight, and fetal or neonatal death .
Because of its immune incompetence prior to midpregnancy, the fetus is less likely to manifest the immunological inflammatory response characteristic of congenital infection before this time .
However, congenital infection is still presumed in all cases, and thus treatment is imperative.
When vertical transmission occurs, severe congenital syphilis progresses along a continuum.
Hepatic abnormalities are followed by anemia, thrombocytopenia, and then ascites and hydrops.
Stillbirth remains a major complication .
The newborn may have jaundice with petechiae or purpuric skin lesions, lymphadenopathy, rhinitis, pneumonia, myocarditis, nephrosis, or long-bone involvement .
Figure 68-3.
Congenital syphilis.
A. A desquamating skin rash known as pemphigus syphiliticus may be seen.
B. Neonatal lower-extremity long-bone radiographs show a “moth-eaten” appearance (arrows).
C. Enlarged hydropic placenta of a syphilis-infected pregnancy.
With syphilitic infection, the placenta becomes large and pale.
Microscopically, villi lose their characteristic arborization, and blood vessels diminish or are obliterated as a result of endarteritis and stromal cell proliferation.
Sheffield and colleagues (2002c) described these villi in more than 60 percent of placentas from women with untreated syphilis at delivery.
Examination of the umbilical cord may reveal necrotizing funisitis, and spirochetes may be microscopically seen after
immunohistochemical staining .
# Diagnosis.
In their 2018 guidance, the United States Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) recommends screening for syphilis in all pregnant women to prevent congenital infection.
Testing is performed at the first prenatal visit.
In populations with a high prevalence of syphilis or in persons with the risk factors noted earlier, serological testing is repeated at 28 weeks’ gestation and again at delivery .
Treponema pallidum cannot be cultured from clinical specimens.
However, direct diagnosis of early-stage disease can be completed by darkfield microscopic examination, NAAT, or immunostaining of lesion exudate, tissue, or body fluid.
These methods are not widely available and are less sensitive for blood specimens .
In practice, a diagnosis is made with serological testing coupled with clinical findings.
Two types of serological tests are employed to diagnose and screen, and sequential use of both reduces false-positive diagnoses.
If the first is positive, the second type is then performed.
This combination identifies infection but by itself does not determine disease stage.
Instead, disease stage is assigned based on initial serological titer levels, patient history of potential exposures and prior treatment, and clinical-stage definitions, described earlier.
Traditionally, the first type is nontreponemal testing, and either the Venereal Disease Research Laboratory (VDRL) or the rapid plasma reagin (RPR) is selected.
Both tests measure patient immunoglobulin M and G (IgM and IgG) antibodies formed against cardiolipin that is released from damaged host cells and possibly also from treponemes.
Notably, these same antibodies can also be produced in response to other acute events that include recent vaccination, febrile illness, and pregnancy itself.
They can be produced in response to chronic conditions such as intravenous (IV) drug abuse, systemic lupus erythematosus, aging, leprosy, or cancer.
As such, these all serve as potential sources of false-positive results .
Conversely, early infection may be characterized by very high levels of antibody or antigen, which prevent immune complex formation and lead to false-negative test results.
This is the prozone effect.
Alternatively, seroconversion occurs at around the third week of infection but can take up to 6 weeks .
Thus, women with very early primary syphilis can have initially false-negative serological test results.
With positive nontreponemal test results, findings are quantified and expressed as titers.
Because titers reflect disease activity, they rise during early syphilis and often exceed levels of 1:32 in secondary syphilis.
A nontreponemal titer is usually measured on the day of treatment initiation.
Subsequent titer declines are considered relative to this day-of-treatment titer.
The second type of serological test is used to confirm the presence of T pallidum–specific antibodies.
These tests include fluorescent treponemalantibody absorption tests (FTA-ABS), T pallidum passive particle agglutination (TP-PA) tests, and various immunoassays .
Of note, these treponemal-specific tests generally remain positive throughout life, even after treatment.
Antibodies may be detected by treponemal assays up to a few weeks earlier than those detected by nontreponemal tests .
Traditionally, nontreponemal tests are used first for screening, and results are then confirmed by a treponemal-specific test.
In a newer reverse sequence strategy, screening begins first with a treponemal-specific test.
Each of the serological tests has limitations, including false-positive and negative results.
Management of discordant finding with this latter sequence is shown in Table 68-1.
Notably, both approaches are suitable if a screening, follow-up, and treatment program is in place.
Table 68-1.
Interpretation of Serologic Tests Using Reverse Sequence Syphilis Screening In contrast to these laboratory tests, rapid “point-of-care” (POC) syphilis screening of blood or serum samples is available.
Most tests are treponemalspecific, and positive POC
results can then be confirmed by laboratorybased tests.
In hard-to-reach populations, immediate treatment of women with positive POC results is associated with lower rates of stillbirth, neonatal death, and congenital syphilis .
This practice, however, risks overtreating previously cured women who still have residual persistent treponemal antibodies.
This limitation may be overcome by newer POC dual tests, which simultaneously assess nontreponemal and treponemal antibodies .
Following maternal diagnosis, sonographic evaluation is performed for fetuses >20 weeks’ gestation to search for signs of congenital syphilis.
Rac and associates (2014) noted that 31 percent of infected women diagnosed at ≥18 weeks’ gestation had fetuses with abnormal sonographic findings.
Hepatomegaly, placental thickening, hydramnios, ascites, hydrops fetalis, and elevated middle cerebral artery Doppler velocimetry measurements suggest fetal infection.
Before 20 weeks, treatment is highly successful, and abnormal sonographic findings are rare .
With maternal infection and with a fetus of viable age that shows sonographic findings, antepartum fetal heart rate (FHR) monitoring prior to antibiotic treatment is recommended.
If the FHR tracing is reassuring, antibiotic therapy can proceed.
In contrast, spontaneous late decelerations or a nonreactive FHR tracing likely reflects an extremely ill fetus that may poorly tolerate a Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction, described subsequently.
In this extreme case, consultation with a neonatologist regarding a plan of delaying treatment, pursuing delivery, and then treating in the nursery is a consideration .
After antibiotic treatment, further sonographic surveillance or antenatal testing of fetal well-being is determined in consultation with specialists.
Following adequate treatment, sonographic signs of congenital infection resolve over weeks to months, and delivery is reserved for usual obstetrical indications .
In fetuses without initial signs of congenital syphilis, subsequent sonographic evaluations are reserved for other fetal indications.
# Treatment.
Syphilis therapy during pregnancy aims to eradicate maternal infection and to prevent or treat congenital syphilis.
Parenteral penicillin G benzathine remains the preferred treatment for all stages of syphilis during pregnancy .
A second dose of benzathine penicillin G may be given 1 week after the initial dose in patients with early-stage syphilis or sonographic signs of congenital infection.
This aims to reduce the risk of fetal treatment failure and is our current practice at Parkland Hospital.
High maternal serological titers, preterm delivery, and delivery shortly after antepartum therapy are all risks for failure of maternal treatment to prevent neonatal infection .
Women should abstain from sexual contact for 7 days, until all skin/mucous membrane lesions heal, and until sexual partners are treated.
Table 68-2.
Recommended Treatment for Pregnant Women with Syphilis There are no proven alternatives to penicillin therapy during pregnancy.
Some data support a 1-g daily IV dose of ceftriaxone for 10 days (Cao, 2017; Liang, 2016).
Tetracyclines are effective but not recommended during pregnancy, because of the risk for offspring teeth discoloration.
Following treatment of syphilis before 24 weeks’ gestation, nontreponemal tests are repeated in either the third trimester or no sooner than 8 weeks after treatment unless reinfection is suspected .
Following treatment after 24 weeks, nontreponemal titers may be repeated in the third trimester in some cases and are repeated at delivery.
Adequate serological response to treatment is suggested by a fourfold decline in nontreponemal titer and resolution of any clinical symptoms.
A fourfold decline in titer is more likely to occur following treatment of earlystage syphilis, which typically has high nontreponemal titers.
Absence of a fourfold decline does not itself determine treatment failure, particularly when the initial nontreponemal titer is <1:8.
Titers are best interpreted in conjunction with
clinical history and by those experienced with treatment of syphilis in pregnancy.
Because VDRL titers do not correspond directly to RPR titers, consistent use of the same test for surveillance is recommended.
Some successfully treated patients may still exhibit persistently lowlevel positive titers, which are referred to as “serofast.
This state is more likely in older individuals, those with lower initial nontreponemal antibody titers, and those with later stages of syphilis (Seña, 2015).
In some instances, a woman may present without symptoms but describes recent sexual contact with a person who has been diagnosed with syphilis.
She should be evaluated clinically and serologically.
If their sexual contact occurred within the preceding 90 days, the gravida is treated presumptively for early syphilis, even if serological test results are negative.
This accounts for early infection but before seroconversion.
If contact was more than 90 days ago, treatment is based on serological results.
Penicillin Reactions Women with a history of penicillin allergy should have either an oral stepwise penicillin-dose challenge or skin testing performed to confirm the risk of IgE-mediated anaphylaxis.
If confirmed, penicillin desensitization is recommended and followed by benzathine penicillin G treatment .
Table 68-3.
Penicillin Allergy—Oral Desensitization Protocol for Patients with a Positive Skin Test Distinct from allergy, the Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction can develop following penicillin treatment in most women with primary syphilis and approximately half with secondary infection.
Uterine contractions, mild maternal temperature elevation, decreased fetal movement, and FHR decelerations are findings.
Treatment is supportive with antipyretics as needed, hydration, and oxygen supplementation .
In a study of 50 gravidas who received benzathine penicillin G for syphilis, the incidence of Jarisch-Herxheimer reactions was 40 percent .
Of the 31 women monitored electronically, 42 percent developed regular uterine contractions, and 39 percent developed variable decelerations.
All contractions resolved within 24 hours.
Thus, for fetuses of viable gestational age, consideration is given to administering the first dose of antibiotic in labor and delivery to permit continuous fetal monitoring for at least 24 hours when the fetus has sonographic signs of syphilis (Adhikari, 2020; Wendel, 2002).
With or without sonographic signs of fetal infection, patients are counseled on symptoms of the Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction prior to syphilis treatment and are encouraged to seek evaluation if they develop.
Gonorrhea.
# Infection Rates and Effects.
Of reportable bacterial STIs, those caused by Neisseria gonorrhoeae are the second most common.
The incidence in women in the United States has continued to rise since 2015, and the highest rates are in those aged 15 to 24 years .
Among women giving birth in 2018, the rate was 310 cases per 100,000 live births .
In most gravidas, infection is limited to the cervix, urethra, and periurethral and greater vestibular (Bartholin) glands.
Acute salpingitis is rare in pregnancy.
However, pregnant women account for a disproportionate number of disseminated gonococcal infections .
Gonococcal infection can have adverse effects in any trimester.
In affected women, associated rates of preterm delivery, preterm prelabor ruptured membranes (PPROM), low birthweight, and perinatal mortality are slightly higher than in those without infection .
Miscarriage rates are not increased.
However, untreated gonococcal cervicitis is associated with septic abortion and with uterine infection after surgical abortion .
Vertical transmission of gonorrhea mainly occurs through fetal contact with cervical infection during birth.
The predominant sequela is gonococcal ophthalmia neonatorum, which can lead to corneal scarring, ocular perforation, and blindness.
Transmission rates are high and approximate 40 percent .
Outlined in Chapter 32 (p. 593), ocular prophylaxis is provided to all newborns (U.S. Preventive Services Task Force,
2019a). # Screening and Treatment.
Pregnant women who live in high-prevalence areas or who are at risk for gonorrhea should undergo first-trimester screening.
Risk factors include age ≤25 years, prior or current STI, sex work, a new or nonmonogamous partner, a partner with an STI, multiple sexual partners, and inconsistent condom use if not monogamous .
Gonococcal infection is a marker for concomitant chlamydial infection.
Thus, if chlamydial testing is unavailable, presumptive chlamydial therapy is given to women treated for gonorrhea.
Screening for gonorrhea in women is by culture or NAAT.
NAATs have replaced culture in most laboratories, and kits are available for specific collection from the vagina, endocervix, or urine.
Of these, vaginal or cervical samples are preferred, as urine collection may detect up to 10 percent fewer infections .
If used, the initial urine stream, not midstream, is collected.
In women with vaginal symptoms and who practice anal intercourse, rectal screening can be considered.
One study of nonpregnant women at urban STI clinics found that approximately 20 percent of rectal chlamydia and gonorrhea infections would be missed if only cervical, vaginal, or urine samples were obtained .
NAATs are also suitable for diagnosis of rectal or pharyngeal disease .
An ultrarapid NAAT for gonorrhea and chlamydia has been approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for point-of-care use.
It performs similarly to laboratory-based testing, and results are available in approximately 30 minutes (Food and Drug Administration, 2021; Van Der Pol, 2020).
This test has not been rigorously studied in pregnant women but may reduce barriers to prompt treatment in patients with limited access to care.
Gonorrhea treatment continues to evolve due to the ability of N gonorrhoeae to develop antimicrobial resistance .
In gravidas, if chlamydia has not been excluded, a 1-g oral dose of azithromycin is added.
Patients abstain from intercourse for 7 days after they and their sexual partner(s) have completed treatment.
Table 68-4.
Treatment of Gonorrhea in Pregnancya,b For those with pharyngeal infection, non-ceftriaxone-based regimens have higher failure rates.
Thus, those with contraindications to ceftriaxone merit infectious disease specialist consultation.
With pharyngeal infection, a test-of-cure 1 to 2 weeks after treatment is recommend.
This is unnecessary after treatment of urogenital or rectal gonorrhea.
To exclude reinfection, repeat testing is recommended 3 months after treatment of any gonorrhea infection.
For any woman treated for gonorrhea in the first trimester and for any uninfected woman who is at high risk for gonococcal infection, testing is repeated in the third trimester (American Academy of Pediatrics, 2017; Workowski, 2021).
Sexual contacts are treated.
Expedited therapy, discussed with chlamydial infection, is a less-desirable option due to the now-preferred injectable regimen.
If elected, a single, oral, 800-mg dose of cefixime is provided.
If chlamydia is not excluded, oral doxycycline, 100 mg twice daily for 7 days, is added.
# Disseminated Gonococcal Infections.
Gonococcal bacteremia may cause disseminated infections that manifest as petechial or pustular skin lesions, arthralgias, or septic arthritis.
Antimicrobial susceptibility testing is requested for isolates cultured from infection sites.
For treatment, ceftriaxone, 1 g IV or intramuscularly, is given every 24 hours and continued for 24 to 48 hours after clinical improvement .
An oral agent that is selected based on susceptibility testing is then provided to complete 1 week of therapy.
Prompt recognition and antimicrobial treatment will usually yield favorable outcomes in pregnancy .
Meningitis and endocarditis are rare in pregnancy, but they may be fatal.
For gonococcal endocarditis, ceftriaxone 1 to 2 g IV every 12 hours should be continued for at least 4 weeks, and for meningitis, 10 to 14 days.
In all these cases, a single, 1-g, oral dose of azithromycin is provided to treat potential chlamydial co-infection .
Chlamydial
Infection.
# Infection Rates and Effects.
Chlamydia trachomatis is an obligate intracellular bacterium that attaches to columnar or transitional-cell epithelium to cause urogenital infection.
It is the most common reportable STI in the United States.
The chlamydial infection rate was 694 cases per 100,000 women in 2019, and the highest rate is in those aged 15 to 24 years .
Among women giving birth in 2018, the rate was 1844 cases per 100,000 live births .
Most infected pregnant women are asymptomatic, but a third have urethral syndrome, urethritis, or greater vestibular (Bartholin) gland infection .
Mucopurulent cervicitis may result from chlamydial or gonococcal infection or both.
Uncommon manifestations during pregnancy are endometritis, salpingitis, reactive arthritis, and Reiter syndrome.
The role of chlamydial infection in pregnancy complications remains controversial.
It is disputed whether untreated cervical infection raises rates of preterm delivery, PPROM, low birthweight, or perinatal mortality (Andrews, 2000; Reekie, 2018; Silva, 2011).
Chlamydial infection is not associated with a greater risk of chorioamnionitis or with peripartum pelvic infection (Berman, 1987; Gibbs, 1987).
However, delayed postpartum uterine infection has been described by Hoyme and associates (1986).
The syndrome, which develops 2 to 3 weeks postpartum, is distinct from early postpartum metritis.
It is characterized by vaginal bleeding or discharge, low-grade fever, and uterine tenderness.
Infection at delivery poses a higher risk to the newborn than to the mother.
Vertical transmission leads to infection in 8 to 44 percent of neonates delivered vaginally from affected women .
Of neonatal infections, conjunctivitis is the most common .
Perinatal transmission to newborns can also cause pneumonia.
# Screening and Treatment.
Currently, the USPSTF and the American Academy of Pediatrics and American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) recommend chlamydia screening for all women at the first prenatal visit .
The College further suggests testing in the third trimester for those treated in the first trimester, all women aged ≤25 years, and those aged >25 years with behavioral factors, which mirror those for gonorrhea.
Dionne-Odom and associates (2020) reported a reinfection rate of 10 percent in pregnant women successfully treated before delivery.
Diagnosis is made predominantly by NAAT rather than culture.
Of samples for NAAT, vaginal or cervical samples are preferred, because urine collection may detect up to 10 percent fewer infections (Papp, 2014; Wiesenfeld, 2017).
However, Roberts and associates (2011) evaluated NAAT of urine specimens compared with cervical secretions in more than 2000 pregnant women and found them to be equivalent.
As with gonorrhea, the first portion of the urine stream is collected.
Currently recommended treatment regimens for chlamydial infections are shown in Table 68-5.
Azithromycin is first-line treatment in pregnancy.
The fluoroquinolones and doxycycline are usually avoided in pregnancy, and erythromycin estolate is contraindicated because of drug-related hepatotoxicity.
Table 68-5.
Oral Treatment of Chlamydia trachomatis Infection in Pregnancya A test of cure is repeated 4 weeks after therapy completion in pregnancy.
Earlier NAAT may resample dead but treated organisms .
A positive result can reflect a reinfection, a false-positive case from dead organisms, or treatment failure or noncompliance.
Fortunately, drug resistance is rare for C trachomatis .
Our practice is to retreat women with positive test-of-cure results.
Additionally, repeat screening 3 months after treatment is recommended to exclude reinfection .
# Expedited Partner Therapy.
To prevent STI transmission, guidelines for expedited partner therapy (EPT) have been created by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2006a) and are endorsed by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a).
With EPT, treatment is provided to persons who were sexual contacts of the patient within the prior 60 days.
Partner
therapy may be a prescription slip for the partner, direct medication administration to the partner and patient simultaneously, or a medication packet delivered to the partner(s) by the patient.
Ideally, EPT does not replace traditional partner referral to allow their medical assessment, counseling, and screening for other STIs.
EPT is acceptable for treatment of sexual contacts with chlamydial infection.
Because of new guidelines that recommend injectable ceftriaxone alone, EPT for gonorrhea is less desirable unless the partner(s) will be unable or unwilling to seek treatment .
Fewer data are available to assess this strategy for trichomoniasis (Kissinger, 2006; Schwebke, 2010).
EPT is not recommended for syphilis.
EPT is legally permissible or potentially allowable in all states.
Links to specific state laws are found at: www.cdc.gov/std/ept/legal/default.htm.
Notably, the risk of litigation following an adverse outcome may be elevated when a practice has uncertain legal status or is outside formally accepted community practice standards Medication-related adverse reactions among treated partners is rare .
The goal of EPT in pregnancy is to lower reinfection rates and adverse maternal and neonatal effects.
A recent study at Parkland Hospital showed that EPT did not lower the chlamydia reinfection rate prior to delivery .
Partner compliance, cost, and education may be factors (McCool-Myers, 2020; Slutsker, 2020).
Herpes Simplex Virus.
# Adult Disease.
Orogenital HSV infection manifests as shallow ulcers on affected mucosa.
Infection stems from either of two different HSV viruses that are distinguished based on immunological differences.
Yet, the two viruses have significant DNA homology, and thus prior infection with one type attenuates a primary infection with the other.
Type 2 HSV is recovered almost exclusively from the genital tract and is usually transmitted sexually.
Type 1 is responsible for most nongenital infections and typically is acquired in childhood.
However, more than half of the new cases of genital herpes in adolescents and young adults are now caused by HSV-1 infection .
This rise in the prevalence of HSV-1 genital disease may stem from an increase in rates of oral-genital sexual practices.
Another explanation is that HSV-1 acquisition has declined in childhood as a result of improved living conditions and hygiene .
Without prior exposure, young people without HSV-1 antibodies are rendered susceptible to genital acquisition of HSV-1 or -2.
Genital herpes simplex virus affects an estimated 19 million adolescents and adults in the United States .
In pregnant women, the HSV-2 seroprevalence was 21 percent, and for HSV-1, it was 59 percent from 2007 to 2014.
However, from 1999 to 2014, pregnant women with fewer sex partners were increasingly seronegative for both virus types .
Seronegative pregnant women have a 4 to 5 percent risk to acquire either serotype during pregnancy (Brown, 1997; Kulhanjian, 1992).
For those who are already HSV-1 seropositive, acquisition risk for HSV-2 approximates 2 percent .
Once transmitted by contact, viruses replicate at the entry site.
Following mucocutaneous infection, the virus moves retrograde along sensory nerves.
It remains latent in cranial nerves or dorsal spinal ganglia, but recurrences are common.
HSV infections may be categorized into three groups.
First-episode primary infection describes the case in which HSV-1 or 2 is isolated from a lesion in the absence of HSV-1 or -2 serological antibodies.
The typical incubation period of 6 to 8 days may be followed by a papular eruption with itching or tingling that then becomes painful and vesicular.
Multiple vulvar and perineal lesions may or may not coalesce but then ulcerate .
Associated inguinal adenopathy can be severe.
Many women do not present with typical lesions, and abraded or knife-cut lesions instead may be found.
Cervical involvement is common, although it may be unapparent clinically.
Transient systemic influenza-like symptoms or isolated high fevers with or without painful lesions are frequent and
attributed to viremia.
Uncommonly, women require hospitalization for febrile syndrome or for pain control of widespread ulceration.
Hepatitis, encephalitis, or pneumonia infrequently develop, and disseminated disease is rare.
After 2 to 4 weeks, all signs and symptoms of infection disappear.
In contrast to these classic symptoms, the percentage of asymptomatic primary HSV-2 genital infections may reach 90 percent .
Figure 68-4.
First-episode primary genital herpes simplex virus infection.
As shown by the arrows, lesions may be vesicular, may be crusted, or may be shallow ulcers.
First-episode nonprimary infection is diagnosed when one HSV type is isolated from a lesion in a woman who has only antibodies to the other HSV serotype.
For example, prior childhood HSV-1 infection likely provides cross-reacting antibodies to blunt the effects of new HSV-2 acquisition.
Compared with primary infection, nonprimary infections produce fewer systemic manifestations or lesions, less pain, and briefer duration of lesions and viral shedding.
Recurrent disease is characterized by isolation of HSV-1 or -2 from the genital tract in women who carry antibodies to the same serotype.
During the latency period, in which viral particles reside in nerve ganglia, reactivation is common and mediated through poorly understood stimuli.
In general, lesions are fewer in number, are less tender, and shed virus for a shorter period than those of primary infection.
Typically, they recur at the same sites.
Recurrences are most frequent in the first year after initial infection, and rates slowly decline subsequently .
Gravidas with a known prior history of genital HSV often experience recurrences .
Asymptomatic viral shedding is defined by the absence of clinical findings.
Most infected women shed virus intermittently over time, and most HSV transmission to a partner occurs during these periods of asymptomatic viral shedding.
# Vertical Transmission.
HSV poses a higher risk to the newborn than to the mother.
Thus, strategies aim to curb rates of vertical transmission, which may occur by three routes: (1) peripartum in 85 percent, (2) postnatal in 10 percent, or (3) intrauterine in 5 percent .
Evidence does not suggest an obvious link between HSV infection and miscarriage .
Peripartum transmission is by far the more frequent route of infection, and the fetus is exposed to virus shed from the lower genital tract.
HSV-1 or -2 invades the uterus following membrane rupture or is transmitted by contact at delivery.
The newborn is mainly infected, but rare cases of maternal endometritis have been described (Hollier, 1997; McGill, 2012).
Of neonatal manifestations, infection may localize to the skin, eye, or mouth—SEM disease—in approximately 40 percent of cases.
Instead, central nervous system (CNS) disease with encephalitis is seen in 30 percent.
Last, disseminated disease that involves multiple major organs is found in 32 percent.
Localized infection is usually associated with a good outcome.
Conversely, even with acyclovir treatment, disseminated infection has a mortality rate of nearly 30 percent (Corey, 2009; Kimberlin, 2011).
Of disseminated or cerebral infection survivors, serious developmental and CNS morbidity is seen in 20 to 50 percent.
In the United States, the neonatal infection rate ranges from 1 to 5 cases in 10,000 births (Donda, 2019; Mahant, 2019).
Most infected newborns are born to mothers with no reported history of HSV infection .
The risk of neonatal infection correlates with the presence of HSV in the genital tract, HSV type, invasive obstetrical procedures, and stage of maternal infection (Brown, 2005, 2007).
Neonates born to women who acquire genital HSV near the time of delivery have a 30- to 50-percent risk of infection.
This is attributed to higher viral loads and the lack of transplacental protective antibodies (Brown, 1997, 2000).
With recurrent HSV, the neonatal infection rate is <1 percent (Pasternak, 2010; Prober, 1987).
Postpartum transmission is uncommon and passed to the newborn by contact with an infected mother,
family member, or health-care worker.
The clinical presentation mirrors that with peripartum transmission.
In-utero transmission of HSV-1 or HSV-2 is rare and is part of the TORCH (toxoplasmosis, other, rubella, cytomegalovirus, herpes virus) group of infections.
Intrauterine HSV infection classically leads to disease involving the skin (blisters, scarring), the CNS (hydranencephaly, microcephaly, intracranial calcification), or the eyes (chorioretinitis, microphthalmia).
Bone and viscera can be involved .
Congenital infection with HSV or another TORCH infection is considered in a fetus with early or severe growth restriction, microcephaly, intracranial anomalies or calcifications, or hepatomegaly.
If sonographic findings are identified, amniocentesis is recommended, and maternal HSV serological testing is done.
Analysis of amnionic fluid for HSV-1 and HSV-2 serotypes is by NAAT (PCR) and culture .
# Diagnosis.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020d) and USPSTF (2016) recommend against routine serological HSV screening in asymptomatic gravidas.
However, for a woman with a reported history of genital or oral lesions, a serological HSV diagnosis is sought.
For women with either suspicious ulcers or sonographic findings suggestive of congenital infection, direct virological testing, described next, is performed along with serological testing for HSV.
Testing for syphilis and other STIs is also considered for women with genital ulcers.
Direct virological tests, which are either PCR or culture, are performed on a specimen from a mucocutaneous lesion or from amniocentesis.
For mucocutaneous lesions, PCR assays are more sensitive, the results generally are available in 1 to 2 days, and specimen handling is easier.
The sensitivity of culture for detecting HSV is relatively low as vesicular lesions begin to ulcerate and then crust.
Also, results sometimes are not available for 7 to 14 days .
Regardless of the test performed, HSV viral types should be differentiated .
Importantly, a negative culture or PCR result does not exclude infection.
In contrast, false-positive results are rare.
For amnionic fluid assessment, both culture and PCR are recommended .
Serological assays detect antibodies produced against the specific HSV glycoproteins, G1 and G2.
These proteins evoke type-specific antibody responses to HSV-1 and HSV-2 infection, respectively, and they reliably differentiate the two serotypes.
Antibody detection confirms clinical infection and may reflect a carrier state in an asymptomatic patient.
IgG antibodies develop 1 to 2 weeks after a primary infection and then persist.
Serological testing may be falsely negative in the case of early infection but may also establish a nonprimary infection.
For this reason, direct detection of the virus in a lesion with concomitant type-specific serological testing is helpful for clinical interpretation and counseling.
Sensitivity and specificity of glycoprotein-based IgG tests approach 90 to 100 percent .
IgM antibody detection is not a useful test, and antibodies may be detected with recurrent episodes.
# Management.
In nonpregnant patients, antiviral therapy with acyclovir, valacyclovir, or famciclovir is used to treat first-episode orogenital herpes.
Oral or parenteral preparations attenuate clinical infection and viral shedding duration.
Chronic suppressive therapy also is an option to limit recurrences and to reduce heterosexual transmission .
In pregnant women, acyclovir and valacyclovir are safe (Briggs, 2022; Stone, 2004).
Data are limited regarding fetal effects with famciclovir.
For a primary outbreak during pregnancy, women may be given antiviral therapy to attenuate and decrease the duration of symptoms and viral shedding .
Women with HIV co-infection may require a longer duration of treatment.
Those with severe or disseminated HSV are given IV acyclovir, 5 to 10 mg/kg every 8 hours for 2 to 7 days until clinically improved.
This is followed by oral antiviral drugs to complete at least 10 days of total therapy .
For intense discomfort, oral analgesics
and topical lidocaine ointment may provide some relief.
Comorbid urinary retention is rare but can be treated briefly with an indwelling bladder catheter.
Table 68-6.
Oral Antiviral Medications for Herpesvirus Infection in Pregnancya For recurrent HSV infections during pregnancy, antiviral treatment is provided mainly for symptom relief .
Although uncommon, acyclovir resistance has been reported, predominantly in immunocompromised patients .
Of precautions during pregnancy, amniocentesis, percutaneous cord blood sampling, or transabdominal chorionic villus sampling may be performed even with active genital lesions.
Transcervical procedures may best be delayed until lesions have resolved .
# Peripartum Shedding Prophylaxis.
To diminish vertical transmission risks, cesarean delivery is indicated for women with active genital lesions or prodromal symptoms.
Several studies have shown that acyclovir or valacyclovir suppression initiated at 36 weeks’ gestation for gravidas with recurrences during pregnancy lowers the number of HSV outbreaks at term.
The goal is to decrease the need for cesarean delivery .
This suppressive therapy will also decrease viral shedding (Scott, 2002; Sheffield, 2006; Watts, 2003).
One systematic review evaluated acyclovir prophylaxis given from 36 weeks to delivery to women with HSV recurrence during pregnancy.
Sheffield and colleagues (2003) found that suppressive therapy was associated with significantly lower rates of clinical HSV recurrence, cesarean delivery for HSV recurrences, total HSV detection, and asymptomatic shedding.
Subsequent studies using valacyclovir suppression showed similar results (Andrews, 2006; Sheffield, 2006).
Because of these studies, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020d) recommends viral suppressive therapy to begin at ≥36 weeks’ gestation for women with a clinical history of genital herpes.
Suppression continues until delivery.
Notably, despite maternal antiviral suppression, several cases of atypical neonatal herpes infection have been reported .
On presentation for delivery, a woman with a history of HSV should be questioned regarding current prodromal symptoms.
A careful examination of the vulva, vagina, and cervix is performed for all, and women without genital lesions may proceed with labor and delivery.
Usual obstetrical management, including invasive fetal monitoring, is supported in the absence of active lesions or prodromal symptoms .
Suspicious lesions should be swabbed for culture or NAAT evaluation.
Cesarean delivery is indicated for women with suspicious genital lesions or prodromal symptoms.
Moreover, for women with a clinical recurrence at delivery, there is no absolute duration of membrane rupture beyond which the fetus would not benefit from cesarean delivery .
Cesarean delivery is not recommended for women with a history of HSV infection but no active genital disease at the time of delivery.
Moreover, an active lesion in a nongenital area can be covered by an occlusive dressing, and vaginal delivery is allowed.
With PPROM, no evidence suggests that external lesions cause ascending fetal infection.
However, antiviral treatment during expectant care is recommended.
Major and associates (2003) described expectant management in 29 such women at gestational ages <31 weeks.
No cases of neonatal HSV developed, and the maximum infection risk was calculated to be 10 percent.
Women with active HSV lesions may breastfeed if the breast skin has no lesions.
Strict hand washing is essential.
Valacyclovir and acyclovir may be used for symptomatic maternal lesions during breastfeeding, as drug concentrations in breast milk are low .
Human Papillomavirus.
# Maternal Infection and Prevention.
This is a common STI, and numerous serotypes infect the lower genital tract.
In the United States from 2005 to 2006, the overall HPV prevalence was 40 percent in females aged 14 to 59 years .
Prevalence is highest in younger women, and some of this seroprevalence now reflects HPV vaccination in this age group .
Reproductive-aged women often become
infected within a few years of sexual activity onset, and most infections are asymptomatic and transient.
High-risk types are those with the most oncogenic potential.
Of these, HPV types 16 and 18 are often associated with lower reproductive tract dysplasia .
Mucocutaneous genital warts termed condyloma acuminata are usually caused by types 6 and 11.
The clear link between HPV infection and cervical neoplasia led to development of vaccines that reduce cervical cancer risk .
Although three vaccines are licensed, only one vaccine is currently available in the United States.
Gardasil 9 is a nonavalent HPV vaccine against serotypes 6, 11, 16, 18, 31, 35, 45, 52, and 58.
This vaccine is not recommended for gravidas.
However, inadvertent exposures do occur, and no adverse pregnancy outcomes are associated (Kharbanda, 2021; Moreira, 2016; Scheller, 2017).
If a woman is found to be pregnant after starting the vaccination series, remaining doses are delayed and given after delivery.
Women who are breastfeeding may be vaccinated.
Gardasil is licensed for females aged 9 to 45 years, and the target age is 11 to 12 years.
It is recommended for those aged 9 to 26 years.
It is suitable for those aged 27 to 45 years, after shared decision-making regarding age-related benefits and risks .
The three-dose series is given on a schedule of 0, 2, and 6 months for those aged older than 15 (Table 10-7, p. 189).
A two-dose regimen is used for younger individuals.
# Condyloma Acuminata Treatment.
Genital warts frequently grow in number and size with pregnancy.
They commonly undergo apoptosis and resolution postpartum.
Rarely, lesions may fill the vagina or cover the perineum and make vaginal delivery or episiotomy difficult.
Genital wart eradication during pregnancy is usually unnecessary unless they are symptomatic.
Therapy is directed toward debulking symptomatic warts yet minimizing treatment toxicity to the mother and fetus.
Trichloroacetic or bichloracetic acid in an 80- to 90-percent solution applied topically weekly is an effective regimen for external warts.
Some prefer cryotherapy, laser ablation, or surgical excision.
Agents that have limited safety data and thus are not recommended in pregnancy include podophyllin resin, podofilox solution or gel, imiquimod cream, and sinecatechins.
# Neonatal Infection.
Vertical transmission rates of HPV to the newborn are minimal.
Juvenileonset recurrent respiratory papillomatosis (JoRRP) is a rare, benign neoplasm of the larynx.
It can cause hoarseness and respiratory distress in children and is most often caused by HPV 6 or 11.
Risks for infection are maternal genital HPV infection and longer labors .
Although many newborns are likely exposed to HPV, few develop JoRRP .
The incidence in 2013 in the United States was 5 cases in 10,000 births, and dropping rates are attributed to HPV vaccination .
The benefit of cesarean delivery for prevention is unknown, and it is not recommended to avert HPV transmission.
Vaginitis.
Pregnant women frequently develop increased vaginal discharge.
This may be a physiological discharge, described in Chapter 4 (p. 54), but should be differentiated from symptomatic vaginitis, which is also common in pregnancy.
Fortunately, normal vaginal flora serve to prevent vaginitis.
To better understand this, normal vaginal microflora composition and function are currently being studied in the Vaginal Human Microbiome Project .
# Bacterial Vaginosis.
Diagnosis Bacterial vaginosis (BV) is a maldistribution of normal vaginal flora.
With BV, numbers of lactobacilli are decreased, and anaerobic bacterial species are overrepresented.
These anaerobes include Gardnerella, Prevotella, Mobiluncus, and Bacteroides species; Atopobium vaginae; and BVassociated bacteria, provisionally named BVAB1, BVAB2, and BVAB3.
These last three are relatively newly recognized bacteria .
Ribosomal RNA gene-sequencing techniques have identified composite communities of vaginal flora, also called the vaginal microbiota.
Five types of these composite communities exist and are referred to as community state
types (CSTs).
A woman can be categorized to one of these five CSTs based on her vaginal microbiota composition .
Researchers have begun to quantify the risk of BV associated with these CST groups.
Specifically, CSTs I, II, III, and V are rich in lactobacilli.
CST IV is a heterogeneous microbiota of strict anaerobes and is associated with BV. CSTs vary racially, and CST IV is the most common in asymptomatic, healthy black women .
Pregnancy-related changes in vaginal microbiota also are being defined and may hold keys to adverse BV-related pregnancy outcomes, discussed subsequently .
Of childbearing-aged women in the United States, nearly 30 percent have BV.
In black women, the prevalence approximates 50 percent .
Most women are asymptomatic.
In those with symptoms, a foul, thin vaginal discharge is a typical complaint.
Associated risk factors are douching, multiple partners, smoking, and altered host immunity (Desseauve, 2012; Koumans, 2007; Murphy, 2016).
For clinical diagnosis of BV, three of the four following Amsel criteria are present: (1) vaginal pH >4.5; (2) a thin, milky, noninflammatory vaginal discharge; (3) >20 percent clue cells seen microscopically; and (4) a fishy odor after addition of 10-percent potassium hydroxide to a vaginal secretion sample .
The last is described as a positive “whiff test” result.
Likewise, alkalinity of seminal fluid and blood are responsible for complaints of foul odor after intercourse and with menses in affected women.
Initially, a vaginal fluid sample is mixed with saline on a glass slide for microscopic evaluation, and this is often called a wet preparation or “wet prep.
Clue cells are vaginal epithelial cells containing many attached bacteria, which create a poorly defined stippled cellular border .
Microscopically, leukocyte numbers are not increased.
The higher vaginal pH stems from the diminished acid production due to a diminished lactobacilli population.
Notably, Trichomonas vaginalis infection also is associated with anaerobic overgrowth and elaborated amines.
Thus, women diagnosed with BV should have no microscopic evidence of trichomoniasis.
Figure 68-5.
A. Bacterial vaginosis.
Microscopy reveals several squamous cells heavily studded with bacteria.
Clue cells are covered to the extent that cell borders are blurred and nuclei are not visible (arrows).
B. Trichomonads (arrows).
The Nugent score, used primarily in research rather than clinical practice, is a system employed for diagnosing BV .
During microscopic examination of a gram-stained vaginal discharge smear, scores are calculated by assessing bacteria staining and morphology.
NAATs to detect the bacterial types found in women with BV have suitable accuracy and may be used for symptomatic women .
However, these tests assess for bacteria that may also be part of normal flora in asymptomatic women.
Moreover, compared with traditional methods, molecular tests have yet to show superior health outcomes but do add substantial cost.
Treatment Adverse pregnancy-related health outcomes associated with BV are preterm birth, PPROM, and postpartum endometritis (Hillier, 1995; Watts, 1990).
It also increases susceptibility to STIs, including HIV (Atashili, 2008; Brotman, 2010).
For women at low risk for preterm birth, however, treatment of BV does not reduce preterm birth rates (Brocklehurst, 2013; Carey, 2000).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2021) and USPSTF (2020) do not recommend routine BV screening of asymptomatic gravidas at low risk for preterm delivery.
For women with prior preterm birth, evidence of screening and treatment benefits are conflicting .
At Parkland Hospital, we do not routinely screen for BV among women with prior preterm birth.
Treatment is reserved for symptomatic women .
Agents not listed are best avoided due to insufficient data regarding their use in pregnancy .
It is still debated whether BV is a sexually transmitted infection, and treatment of a male partner does not lower recurrence rates (Amaya-Guio, 2016; Schwebke, 2021).
Table 68-7.
Treatment of
Bacterial Vaginosis in Pregnancya # Trichomoniasis.
Diagnosis Vaginitis caused by Trichomonas vaginalis is common, and its prevalence in the United States approximates 2 percent in women .
The prevalence is higher in those older than 30 years compared with younger women.
Risks include black race, douching, and greater number of lifetime sexual partners .
Among women, frequent sites of infection include the urethra, endocervix, and vagina.
Those with symptomatic vaginitis often have a purulent discharge, pruritus, vulvovaginal erythema, and colpitis macularis.
The last is often termed a “strawberry cervix” and displays a patchy, maculoerythematous ectocervix.
Trichomonads are flagellated, pear-shaped, motile organisms that are somewhat larger than leukocytes.
These parasites can readily be seen microscopically moving briskly in wet preparation.
Prompt inspection of vaginal secretions is advantageous because trichomonads slow with cooling.
At times, T vaginalis may be found incidentally on a Pap test slide.
Both of these microscopic approaches have low diagnostic sensitivity that approximates 60 percent (Krieger, 1988; Wiese, 2000).
Pap tests can also yield false-positive results.
Thus, Pap test trichomonad findings warrant confirmation with either a wet prep or NAAT.
Of other direct detection methods, culture is expensive, lengthy, and only 75 to 95 percent sensitive (Association of Public Health Laboratories, 2016; Huppert, 2007).
Laboratory NAAT-based evaluation of a vaginal, endocervical, or urine sample is available, is completed in minutes to hours, and offers superior sensitivity of 95 to 100 percent .
Although more costly than wet-preparation microscopy, a NAAT may be a useful, second-line diagnostic test for microscopy-negative samples.
An optimal approach in pregnancy has not been established.
Rapid POC testing is also available but may sacrifice sensitivity for speed.
The OSOM Trichomonas Rapid Test provides results in 10 minutes, is suitable for office use, and has sensitivities of 88 to 98 percent .
Treatment Treatment is reserved for symptomatic women .
Previously, a one-time, 2-g dose of oral metronidazole was used to eradicate T vaginalis.
In nonpregnant women, a large randomized trial compared this traditional therapy against metronidazole, 500 mg orally twice daily for 7 days.
The longer course provided improved efficacy .
New guidelines from the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020g) now recommend this change in nonpregnant women.
The CDC recognizes this regimen for pregnancy.
Table 68-8.
Oral Treatment of Trichomoniasis in Pregnancya,b Reinfection rates among women treated for trichomoniasis are high .
Thus, retesting for T vaginalis is recommended for all sexually active women within 3 months following initial therapy .
Some authors recommend retesting 3 weeks after treatment in pregnancy .
Metronidazole is not teratogenic or fetotoxic, and it may be used in all pregnancy stages (Briggs, 2022; Czeizel, 1998; Workowski, 2021).
The manufacturer recommends against its use during the first trimester .
Fewer data are available for tinidazole, and thus metronidazole is preferred.
For allergic patients, metronidazole desensitization is effective .
With breastfeeding, the longer, lower-dose metronidazole regimen is not associated with adverse infant outcomes .
Perinatal transmission of trichomoniasis by direct contact in the birth canal is rare but may lead to neonatal respiratory or genital infection (Bruins, 2013; Trintis, 2010).
Some studies have linked trichomonal infection with preterm birth .
A few other studies implicate this infection with PPROM and small-for-gestational age newborns .
However, treatment in two randomized studies did not lower preterm birth rates (Klebanoff, 2001; Stringer, 2010).
In sum, treating symptomatic women is reasonable.
For most asymptomatic women during pregnancy, screening is not done.
However, screening at the first prenatal visit and prompt treatment are encouraged for gravidas with comorbid HIV infection.
In this group, T vaginalis infection
may be a risk factor for vertical HIV transmission .
# Candidiasis.
Candida albicans or other candidal species can be identified by culture from the vagina during pregnancy in approximately 20 percent of women.
A link between candidiasis and preterm birth is not robust (Cotch, 1998; Roberts, 2015).
Thus, asymptomatic colonization requires no treatment.
The organism, however, can create a profuse, irritating discharge.
For symptoms, effective treatment is listed in Table 68-9.
In pregnancy, the CDC recommends 7-day regimens and suggests topical rather than oral azoles .
In some women, infection is likely to recur and require repeat treatment.
In these cases, symptomatic infection usually subsides after pregnancy .
Although not preferred treatment, a single, 150-mg oral fluconazole dose is generally not considered teratogenic.
Data showing a small association with cardiac anomalies are conflicting, but more recent evidence is reassuring (Mølgaard-Nielsen, 2013; Zhu, 2020).
In 2019, the FDA noted that reviewed data do not provide conclusive evidence for an increased miscarriage or stillbirth risk.
Table 68-9.
Daily, Intravaginal Agents in 7-Day Regimens for Vulvovaginal Candidiasis Treatment in Pregnancy Human Immunodeficiency Virus.
# Pathogenesis.
For human immunodeficiency viruses, which are HIV-1 and HIV-2, sexual intercourse is the main mode of transmission.
The virus can be passed by blood, and infected mothers may infect their fetuses during labor and delivery or by breast milk.
The primary determinant of transmission is the maternal plasma viral load.
For sexual transmission, the viral HIV envelope binds to mucosal dendritic cells.
These cells then present the viral particle to specific T lymphocytes.
These lymphocytes are defined phenotypically by their cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4) glycoprotein surface antigens.
The CD4 site serves as a receptor for the virus.
Once infected, CD4 T lymphocytes are gradually depleted, which creates an immunodeficiency that is characterized by low serum CD4 counts.
In some infected with HIV, acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) reflects profound immunodeficiency that gives rise to various opportunistic infections and neoplasms.
The incubation period from exposure to clinical disease averages 3 to 6 weeks.
Acute HIV infection is similar to many other viral syndromes and usually lasts less than 10 days.
Common symptoms, if any, include fever, fatigue, rash, headache, lymphadenopathy, pharyngitis, myalgias, nausea, and diarrhea.
After symptoms abate, the level of viremia usually declines to a set point, and patients with the highest viral burden at this time progress more rapidly to AIDS and death.
According to the CDC, AIDS is defined by a CD4 T-cell count <200 cells/μL, by CD4 T cells constituting <14 percent of all lymphocytes, or by one of several AIDS-defining illnesses .
Route of infection, viral strain’s pathogenicity, initial viral inoculum, and the host’s immunological status all affect progression.
# Prenatal HIV Screening.
In the United States, approximately 5000 women with HIV give birth annually .
However, the estimated number of perinatally acquired HIV cases has dropped, and the rate was 0.9 per 100,000 live births in 2018 .
The decline predominantly stems from prenatal HIV testing and antiretroviral therapy (ART) for the woman and then her neonate.
The CDC (2006b) and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020f) recommend prenatal HIV screening using an opt-out approach.
With this, HIV testing is routinely included in antenatal testing, but this testing may be declined.
Women are given information regarding HIV but are not required to sign a specific consent.
This opt-out strategy has raised HIV testing rates and is permitted in every United States jurisdiction .
Repeat screening during the third trimester, preferably before 36 weeks’ gestation, is considered for all pregnant women.
Retesting is recommended in areas where HIV rates exceed 1 case per 1000 pregnant women screened or for those with risk factors.
These include
incarceration, injection drug use, prostitution, a suspected or known HIV-infected sexual partner, a new or multiple sexual partners, or diagnosis of another STI .
The initial laboratory screening test for HIV is an antigen/antibody combination immunoassay that detects antibodies against HIV-1 and HIV-2 and detects HIV-1 p24 antigen .
No further testing is required for specimens that yield negative results on the initial immunoassay unless a known recent exposure to HIV has occurred.
Antibody can be detected in most patients within 1 month of infection, and thus a test for antibodies alone may not exclude early infection.
Instead, for acute primary HIV infection, identification of viral p24 core antigen or viral RNA is necessary.
Specimens with a “reactive” (that is, a positive) antigen/antibody combination immunoassay result should be tested with an antibody immunoassay that differentiates HIV-1 antibodies from HIV-2 antibodies .
The HIV-1/HIV-2 antibody differentiation immunoassay provides results that are reported as positive or negative for HIV-1 antibodies, for HIV-2 antibodies, or for HIV antibodies, undifferentiated.
If these two serial immunoassays (the initial screen and the differentiation assay) are discordant, an HIV-1 NAAT—qualitative or quantitative HIV RNA test—is performed .
Figure 68-6.
Algorithm for HIV testing.
For specimens that are reactive on the initial antigen/antibody combination immunoassay and nonreactive or indeterminate on the HIV-1/HIV-2 antibody differentiation immunoassay, a nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) is performed.
Following a nonreactive HIV-1/HIV-2 antibody differentiation immunoassay, a positive HIV-1 NAAT indicates laboratory evidence for acute HIV-1 infection.
A positive HIV-1 NAAT result following indeterminate HIV-1/HIV-2 antibody differentiation immunoassay indicates the presence of HIV-1 infection confirmed by HIV-1 NAAT.
A negative HIV-1 NAAT result following nonreactive or indeterminate HIV-1/HIV-2 antibody differentiation immunoassay indicates a false-positive result on the initial antigen/antibody combination immunoassay. (Reproduced with permission from Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2018a.
At delivery, women with undocumented HIV status should have a fourthgeneration HIV antigen/antibody combination screening test performed on a blood sample.
A negative screening test result does not need confirmation.
However, in cases of recent HIV exposure, consideration is given to peripartum interventions to reduce perinatal transmission despite negative HIV testing.
Repeat interval testing is recommended to exclude very early infection not identified with the initial screen.
With a positive fourthgeneration HIV testing result, peripartum and neonatal interventions to reduce perinatal transmission are initiated.
These include intravenous zidovudine infusion during labor and avoidance of breastfeeding, although breast milk may be stored until confirmatory test results are available .
Interventions are continued until the results of an antibody differentiation assay—and qualitative or quantitative RNA test if indicated—is known.
Interventions can be discontinued if confirmatory testing is negative.
To confirm a positive result from any initial HIV test, the laboratory testing algorithm in Figure 68-6 is used and begins with the antigen/antibody combination immunoassay.
# Vertical Transmission.
Viral burden and neonatal infection rates are directly related.
In one cohort, neonatal infection was 1 percent with 30,000 copies/mL .
Among 2615 neonates born to mothers taking ART before conception and during pregnancy, no cases of vertical transmission occurred when maternal viral loads were <50 copies/mL at delivery .
Transmission of HIV infection, however, has been observed at all HIV RNA levels, including those that were nondetectable by current assays.
Transplacental HIV transmission can occur early, and the virus has even been identified in specimens from elective
abortion .
Kourtis and colleagues (2001) estimated that 20 percent of vertical transmission occurs before 36 weeks’ gestation, 50 percent in the days before delivery, and 30 percent intrapartum.
Transmission rates for breastfeeding may be as high as 30 to 40 percent and are associated with increasing HIV viral burden (Kourtis, 2006, 2007; Slyker, 2012).
In nonpregnant individuals, concomitant STIs and horizontal HIV transmission are linked.
Evidence also supports that vertical transmission rates may be increased by comorbid STIs (Schulte, 2001; Watts, 2012).
# Antepartum Care.
Pregnant women with HIV infection need special attention and are seen in consultation by physicians with special interest in this field.
An additional resource is the National Perinatal HIV Hotline (1–888–448–8765), which provides free antepartum, intrapartum, or postpartum consultation to providers.
At Parkland Hospital, a pregnant woman with HIV infection is initially assessed with the following: • Standard prenatal laboratory surveys that include serum creatinine, complete blood count, and bacteriuria screening • Plasma HIV RNA quantification, which establishes the “viral load” value, and antiretroviral resistance testing if the viral load is at least 500 to 1000 copies/mL • CD4 T-cell count • Screening for chlamydial infection, gonorrhea, syphilis, and trichomoniasis, if not previously
performed with new HIV diagnosis • Serum hepatic aminotransferase levels • HSV-1 and -2, cytomegalovirus, toxoplasmosis, and hepatitis B and C serological screening • Baseline chest radiograph • Tuberculosis testing with purified protein derivative (PPD) skin testing or with interferon-gamma release assay • Evaluation of need for pneumococcal, hepatitis A, hepatitis B, Tdap, COVID-19, and influenza vaccines • Sonographic evaluation to establish gestational age.
During pregnancy, the risk of HIV transmission does not appear to be increased with amniocentesis or other invasive diagnostic procedures in women receiving effective ART that results in viral suppression .
For women not receiving ART, the risk rises approximately twofold .
If amniocentesis is performed, efforts are taken to avoid passing through the placenta .
Antiretroviral Therapy In overview, the ideal strategy to suppress viral load and minimize vertical HIV transmission includes (1) preconceptional ART, (2) antepartum ART, (3) intrapartum continuation of the antepartum oral ART regimen plus IV zidovudine, and (4) newborn ART prophylaxis.
ART is recommended for all pregnant women with HIV infection, and it should be initiated as early in pregnancy as possible.
Treatment reduces the risk of perinatal transmission regardless of CD4 T-cell count or HIV RNA level.
Regimen adherence is emphasized to help prevent viral drug resistance.
Gravidas are treated with at least three antiretroviral (ARV) agents.
The Panel on Treatment of Pregnant Women with HIV Infection and Prevention of Perinatal Transmission (2021) has issued guidelines for four different scenarios during pregnancy .
The following paragraphs summarize these recommendations.
Table 68-10.
Recommendations for HIV Antiviral Drug Use During Pregnancy First, women already taking ART at pregnancy onset are encouraged to continue their regimen if viral suppression is adequate and if the ARV is safe and tolerated.
Didanosine, stavudine, and full-dose ritonavir, which differs from ritonavir-boosted agents, are exceptions due to pregnancy toxicity but not teratogenicity.
The lopinavir/ritonavir combination is no longer recommended based on risks for preterm and small-for-gestational-age neonates.
Second, women who have never received antiretroviral therapy— antiretroviral naïve—are given ART regardless of trimester.
In general, the starting regimen comprises two nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors that are coupled into a single agent plus either a ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor or an integrase inhibitor.
Third, women who have previously received antiretroviral therapy but are currently not taking
medications should undergo HIV-resistance testing because prior ART use raises the risk of drug resistance.
However, ART is initiated prior to receiving results of these drug-resistance tests.
In this case, initial ART selection should factor results of any prior resistance testing, if available; prior ART regimen; and current ART pregnancy guidelines, that is, those for ART-naïve women.
Drug-resistance testing may then modify the initial regimen.
For these three categories of women taking antepartum ART, therapy surveillance is outlined in Table 68-10.
Most patients with adequate viral response have at least a 1-log viral load decline within 1 to 4 weeks after starting therapy.
Newer integrase inhibitors rapidly decrease viral loads and are useful for women presenting late to prenatal care .
For those who fail to achieve this degree of decline, regimen compliance is assessed, resistance studies are reviewed, and ART modification is considered.
During labor and delivery, an oral ART regimen is continued with sips of water.
Additionally, IV zidovudine is administered to women during labor and before cesarean delivery.
An exception to this addition is the patient who is strictly adherent to her prescribed oral ART regimen and who has an HIV RNA level that was previously documented to be <50 copies/mL at 34 to 36 weeks’ gestation or at 3 to 4 weeks before delivery.
At Parkland Hospital, we administer intrapartum IV zidovudine to all HIV-positive women, regardless of viral load.
A 2-mg/kg loading dose is infused over 1 hour and is followed with zidovudine, 1 mg/kg/hr until delivery.
Women with HIV undergoing a scheduled cesarean delivery are given IV zidovudine as a loading dose followed by 2 more hours of continuous maintenance therapy— a total of 3 hours of infused zidovudine prior to surgery.
The fourth group includes women who present in labor and who are taking no ART regimen.
These women are given IV zidovudine intrapartum as just described.
# Delivery Planning.
In some cases, cesarean delivery lowers HIV prenatal transmission rates .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020c) suggests that scheduled cesarean delivery be discussed and recommended for HIV-infected women with HIV-1 RNA load >1000 copies/mL.
Scheduled delivery is recommended at 38 weeks’ gestation in these women to avoid spontaneous labor.
Management of women with either HIV-1 RNA load >1000 copies/mL or unknown viral load who present in labor or with ruptured membranes is individualized.
For these women, IV zidovudine is recommended as previously described.
In the case of early labor, cesarean delivery is preferred to vaginal birth.
For women with HIV RNA load ≤1000 copies/mL, cesarean delivery to reduce the risk of vertical HIV transmission is not recommended and is unlikely to confer additional benefit to women already taking ART and achieving viral suppression (Briand, 2013; Jamieson, 2007).
Vaginal delivery in this group is the goal, and awaiting spontaneous onset of labor is suitable.
Labor is not induced to prevent perinatal HIV transmission.
During labor, artificial membrane rupture, fetal scalp electrode placement, episiotomy, and operative vaginal delivery are performed for standard obstetrical indications but are avoided if possible in women with detectable RNA viral load .
Labor augmentation is used when needed to shorten the interval to delivery to help further lower the transmission risk.
For the benefits described in Chapter 27 (p. 500), delayed cord clamping in preterm neonates is acceptable and may be considered for term newborns.
Neuraxial analgesia is suitable.
Postpartum hemorrhage is best managed with oxytocin and prostaglandin analogues.
Methylergonovine (Methergine) and other ergot alkaloids adversely interact with reverse transcriptase and protease inhibitors to cause severe vasoconstriction.
# Postpartum Care.
Vertical transmission rates rise with breastfeeding, and it generally is not recommended for women with HIV infection in the United States, where formula is readily available .
In
nutritionally deprived countries, where infectious disease and malnutrition are primary causes of infant death, the World Health Organization (2016) recommends exclusive breastfeeding during the first 6 to 12 months.
The Panel on Treatment of Pregnant Women with HIV Infection and Prevention of Perinatal Transmission (2021) strongly recommends that ART regimens not be discontinued postpartum but continued lifelong for the advantages of viral suppression.
Ideally, all those planning pregnancy should be receiving ART and have a viral load below detectable levels before conception.
As one benefit, interpregnancy viral load suppression is associated with less vertical transmission in a subsequent pregnancy (French, 2014; Stewart, 2014).
Reassuringly, for those seeking subsequent pregnancy, when ART is available, repeated pregnancy in a healthy woman with HIV has no significant effect on disease progression .
Transition postpartum to general HIV care is critical to maintain viral suppression .
# Prevention.
For adults without HIV infection but with risks for HIV acquisition, the USPSTF (2019b) recommends offering preexposure prophylaxis (PrEP) to decrease the risk of acquiring HIV.
Risk factors for heterosexually active women without HIV infection are a partner with HIV, syphilis or gonorrhea within the past 6 months, and inconsistent condom use with a high-risk partner.
The last is a partner with injection drug use or with multiple other sexual partners.
Current guidance from the CDC (2018b) emphasizes the use of ART to achieve viral suppression in the infected partner and barrier use as primary methods of preventing horizontal transmission.
However, PrEP for the HIV-negative partner is considered, including during pregnancy to reduce the risk of HIV acquisition and also vertical transmission.
PrEP with tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF)/emtricitabine taken orally daily is acceptable during pregnancy and is encouraged particularly if the HIV viral load of the infected partner is unknown or unsuppressed.
Barrier methods are reinforced.
For conception in HIV-serodiscordant couples, assisted reproductive technologies are available.
In lower-resource settings, acceptable approaches combine safer conception methods.
These include combinations of treatment to achieve viral suppression for the HIV-seropositive partner, PrEP for the HIV-seronegative partner, STI screening and treatment, timed condomless sex during peak fertility days, and self-insemination, (American Society for Reproductive Medicine, 2021; Schwartz, 2019).
If pregnancy is undesired, contraception options are discussed .
Counseling also includes education for decreasing high-risk sexual behaviors to prevent HIV transmission or acquisition and to decrease other STI acquisition.